Speaker 0: Luton Town football fans are celebrating their team being promoted to the Premier League after the play-off final against Coventry City went to penalties. It's the first time that Luton have been in the top flight in the Premier League era, having been relegated the season before it began in 1992. These fans were over the moon.
Speaker 1: The best ever. My dad has dreamt of this for years and years and oh my god to get there. And then, absolute dream.
Speaker 3: Yeah, it was unreal.
Speaker 2: They did so well.
Speaker 3: Absolute scenes and that's what Luton's about really. Unbelievable. Dream come true. Hard games, a battle to get out. Never believed it. So it's just unbelievable.
Speaker 0: Seven people have been charged with the attempted murder of a senior police officer in Northern Ireland. Detective Chief Inspector John Caldwell was shot at a sports centre in Omer in February in front of his young son. The men, aged between 28 and 72, are due to appear before magistrates on Monday. The Home Office says a fault with electronic gates at passport control, which caused serious delays for travellers, has now been fixed. The disruption affecting airports across the UK led to long queues at the start of what is half term for many. The presenter of ITV's This Morning, Holly Willoughby, has released a statement saying she was very hurt to hear that Philip Schofield had lied to her about an affair he'd had with a younger male colleague. Mr Schofield resigned from the broadcaster on Friday. Here's our correspondent, Catherine de Costa.
Speaker 2: In a statement on her Instagram account, Holly said, It's taken time to process yesterday's news. When reports of this relationship first surfaced, I asked Phil directly if this was true and he told it me. it was not. It's been very hurtful, she says, to now find out that this was a lie.
Speaker 0: The French courtroom drama Anatomy of a Fall has won the prestigious Palme d'Or prize at the 76th Cannes Film Festival. Its director, Justine Triet, becomes just the third woman to win the top honour, as Claire Runacres now reports.
Speaker 1: Anatomy of a Fall is a courtroom psychothriller. It stars the German actress Sandra Höhler as a successful novelist accused of killing her husband at a chalet in the French Alps which they've bought to repair their relationship. The only witness to the murder? Their blind son. Unusually, Höhler also stars in the runner-up Grand Jury Prize winner, Zone of Interest. That film follows family life in the concentration camp Auschwitz. She plays the commandant's wife. It's the work of the British director Jonathan Glaser, known for Sexy Beast and Under the Skin, and is based on a novel by Martin Amis.
Speaker 0: It's more Chelsea have won the Women's Super League for the fourth time in a row, holding off the challenge of Manchester United on the final day. A 3-0 win at Reading saw them finish two points clear of United to complete a league and cup double.